Some have have have written and talked
about the surprising phenomenon of of
LLM sounding more human, but I think the
deeper concern is actually that they
sound that we start to sound more like
them and that we start to mirror the
outputs of LLMs. There's a lot of
research suggesting that's already
happening.
>> Yeah.
>> And I think those are that's like where
we start. And again, we've got the uh
anthropology, we've got the experience,
the 2,000 years of wisdom of the church.
We have to start by identifying what are
the problems and opportunities and how
do we apply specifically to those
problems.
Well, Dr. Erin Dominguez, John Breer,
it's fantastic to be with you guys today
uh as the Builder AI conference is going
on. So, thank you for joining me in the
uh Greg Orian studio.
>> Well, thank you. Thank you for having
us. I'm really excited to talk to you
today and really excited to be here
participating in this conference.
How is AI already uh transforming uh
classrooms uh research and
administration?
>> I'm kind of an early adopter kind of guy
with my tech background. So I've been
I've been using all these tools for um
quite some time now and it's made me way
more efficient which is I think the good
aspects of these set of tools. Uh but
no, it's here. It's here to stay and
we've um at the conference last year I
was I was getting ready to launch a new
bachelor's degree and master's degree in
AI for our students from a Catholic
perspective and incorporating our ethics
and the magisterium of the church. And
these students, you know, they they
learn how to code and they learn what
the tools are in the theory. uh but they
also take philosophy classes and
theology classes and integrate our faith
into you know the design uh and use of
these tools which um I was you know
working through those problems of what
does that look like at the conference
last year. So for me personally to see
that launched for this fall semester is
great.
>> And John and how do you see AI
transforming classrooms when when you
talk to teachers or or parents or
administrators?
>> Well, I I'll pick up on two points that
Dr. Dominguez made. The first is that
organically AI has been in our
classrooms for many years now even
pre202.
I mean AI was being uh very subtly used
uh if not uh perceptibly by students or
teachers. Uh so organic use has been
around and certainly since 2022 with
chat GPT uh that that has very much been
a reality that we've had to contend
with. The second point that uh I want to
spend a little bit of time on is the the
pedagogy question because I think that's
been the great opportunity that um that
that has come up in conversation
especially with K12 teachers for many of
them the first gut instinct is oh this
is another cheating tool which of course
if used improperly uh you know a tool
like chatgbt can be a cheating tool um
but it's also a great opportunity to
step back and think about what is our
philosophy of education why do we teach
some of the bigger questions that often
we don't get to wrestle with because
we're so as teachers we're so uh
consumed by the task in front of us. But
the artificial intelligence era has
almost forced those conversations to
come to the four because as soon as you
get into policy writing or adjusting
your syllabi you inherently have to ask
those questions about what will we allow
students to use AI for? What will I
allow myself to use AI for? and then
you're actually having a philosophy like
conversation, a pedagogical conversation
yourself, which to me has been one of
the more exciting um opportunities that
has come up.
>> Yeah, I would agree.
>> And John, where do you see those those
you know questions or or or
philosophical moments occurring?
>> I think in in at least to some degree,
it depends on the type of school. And
this is where it's been very interesting
working, you know, my particular focus
and our focus here is in in Catholic
education, but it's been really
interesting seeing how in different
educational settings, the priority sets
are a little bit different. Um there's
one very common uh or or or well-known
AI uh school uh that exists that has
really leaned into the utilitarian form
of education which is basically a
commodification of skills and and
knowledge and basic facts which from our
our Catholic worldview is completely
misaligned. You know the point of
education is a a formative experience
that prepares a student for disciplehip
uh in their lives and apostilhip and
then ultimately saintthood. That's a
very different version of education
which asks a different set of questions
and again those are the questions that I
think we are able to ask and are forced
to ask now with this set of tools that
can just do things automate things for
us.
>> Yeah, I think that's well said John.
>> Yeah, I love that. And uh and Dr.
Dominguez feels like AI is transforming
every sector that that that it touches.
what in in your uh perspective makes
Catholic education uh uniquely equipped
to lead in the age of AI?
>> Yeah. Um I think it goes and this is how
we actually started our morning session
at the workshop. It goes back to the
question of what is Catholic education
for? What's the difference between
Catholic education and and a secular
education? Is it just that they're
learning the same subjects and then the
students say prayers or go to mass or
what is what is the purpose of Catholic
education? And it's it's what John said.
Um you know and in in our case in the
Catholic University of America, we have
a specific mission written on paper by
Pope Leo the 13th telling us what we're
supposed to do and ordering the bishops
to go make it happen. and that's to
produce worthy ministers and um you know
this the best you know well-formed
citizens for our country in the world.
That's our job as a as a university. Um
and now AI is this this new reality.
It's a set of tools but it's also a
change of an era in the in the same way
um that you know the printing press or
the industrial revolution was. things
are going to be different on the other
side as you as you said it's integrating
into into everything quickly. So we have
from our uh you know from our faith we
have 2,000 years of thought scholarship
and and Christ encounter with Christ on
our side to help us think through these
things. And it's important to uh and
what we can truly do and make a truth
claim about is that we know what a human
being is and we know what we're for. We
know the purpose of our existence. We
know that God has a plan for us, a
unique plan. And we can craft an
education around that. We have. And now
we've got these these set of powerful
and potentially dangerous tools that if
you don't have that perspective of what
a human being is can lead to terrible
things. and my friends who are outside
of the church or who are, you know,
secular humanists and and otherwise just
very good people and don't want to do
bad things, you know, like Google's
don't do evil. Like that's an incomplete
answer to what you should do, but it's
it's not bad to try to not do evil. uh
the the problem the things I struggle
with is um telling the difference
between the simulation of a particular
trait of a human being and and a real
person like how do you tell the
difference between you know these chat
GPT outputs and me and you talking and
we know the answer between the
difference between these things because
God made us you know imo day in this
image and likeness um in order to know
and love him and to be with him. And
this is a tool that we're using. Now,
it's a very dangerous tool just like a
knife can be a very dangerous tool or
you can use it. I could use a knife to
to hurt somebody or I could use it to
cut my stake. So, it's the
intentionality of the the persons. You
have to understand that who who we are,
what are we for and who's my who are my
fellow uh you know travelers on the
earth at this time. Catholic education
gives us the framework and answers for
that that you there's just a limit that
you can't get with secular education.
That that's I think the answer.
>> What do you see going on in in you know
higher education as AI continues to
transform as these technologies continue
to transform the landscape?
>> Yeah, I mean it's a higher education is
in um a moment of crisis itself and I
think this is contributing to it. It's
not the origin of it, but there's a lot
of negative factors right now at play in
in higher ed. Uh you know, there's some
um justly and unjustly
uh
you know, negative views of of higher ed
and I think that it does as a sector I
think does deserve uh some correction.
Um but it's it's under certainly under
attack. Um, and you know, pure
utilitarianism
leads to things like the Holocaust,
right? That's the the ultimate ultimate
result of that type of thinking is just
is horrific, right? Um, so we certainly
must avoid that direction at all costs.
And I think people of goodwill who are
in these secular universities, many of
whom are Catholics themselves but maybe
not in position to change the mission of
the university,
>> um are looking for people like us to to
work with. And I think we see them there
in the room so they can bring that back.
So that that's I think one of our uh one
of our goals here is to be missionaries,
send out missionaries into the world.
>> It strikes me as providential when I
look back at the last roughly 150 years
or so, how God has prepared us for this
moment. We had the industrial revolution
and the blossoming of Catholic social
teaching. We had the theology of the
body unpacked by John Paul II.
And strangely, we have, at least in the
United States, an increasingly secular
world that's actually becoming more
interested, I think, in some of these
deeper existential questions, more open
to the teachings of the church in some
ways. And so in a kind of a strange way,
I think the when you put those factors
together, the church is re again
providentially able to speak directly to
the heart of the matter. And then you
ask the question like how can Catholic
schools and Catholic education broadly
lead? I think it starts by identifying
the problem areas and how do we address
the problems? And for me when I've
worked with teachers, we we talk about
academic integrity, right? That's where
most conversations start.
>> That's what that's true.
>> And it starts there and for some folks
ends there. Uh but I think more deeply
my concerns lie in the disruption that
can take place uh especially in uh the
writing process. Writing is iterative
right? It takes successive attempts
drafting
improperly used AI can reduce the number
of iterations and then severely limit
what you produce. But I think actually
that idea of production is uh also uh
something that's under attack and and
that we need to think about that there's
a distortion taking place and that's the
third that I end up discussing with
teachers is what is the actual ends of
an education again that's where the the
Catholic Church and and our schools and
educational institutions have a
particular answer but most deeply is
this mirroring idea that um some have
have written and talked about the
surprising phenomenon of of LLM sounding
more human. But I think the deeper
concern is actually that they sound that
we start to sound more like them and
that we start to mirror the outputs of
LLM. And there's a lot of research
suggesting that's already happening.
>> And I think those are that's like where
we start. And again, we've got the uh
anthropology, we've got the experience,
the 2,000 years of wisdom of the church.
We have to start by identifying what are
the problems and opportunities and how
do we apply specifically to those
problems.
>> Yeah. Well, I I have I have a I have a
question on kind of the the LLMs and the
algorithms and the automation. So, I was
I was talking to Father Philip Laray uh
from Boston College who who I adore and
we were having a conversation about kind
of the opening days of his of his class.
And in Boston at that time, there was an
advertisement that I don't know John, I
might I might have told you this, but it
really shocked me. It was essentially an
advertisement, you know, on a on a bus
stop and there was a number of these
throughout. And it was a a digitalized
AI. So, it was it was a kind of, you
know, it was it was um like almost like
an animation. So you could tell it was
it was not a real person, but it was of
course in human, you know, human form
and all that. He said, "Don't don't hire
humans. Humans are you shouldn't hire
humans. Hire us robots." And one of the
kids in the um in the classroom came up
to to Father Phillip and I was like,
"Father, what's the point?"
>> Yeah. I think the answer to that is that
um
there's going to be a set of jobs that
um that a machine can do better and is
more efficient. And I think that's why
you're seeing some of these mass
layoffs. But the reason is because these
are very powerful tools that that people
can use. So um that's part of what our
uh program at Catholic University is
meant to do is to prepare the students,
you know, even if you're an English
major, how do you how do you use these
tools? Uh but especially the tech people
who seems to be more at risk, how do you
use these set of tools to work in the
tech industry? And that that we can do
like that's our job as a as a
university. So I think the answer is
teacher students or re you know uh
workforce development. We've been
talking to industries there in the DC
area who have a great workforce that
needs to be re-educated. Like that's
what we do. We can do that too. So um
that's that's the moment. If you don't
get re if you don't get learn these new
tools or if you don't if you come out of
college unprepared then you I think are
going to be
>> at a disadvantage.
And John, when you when you look at um
at AI adoption for for for you know
classrooms and teaching settings,
whether it's in in a high school or
university, where do you draw the line
on where AI should not be used for
Catholic, you know, for Catholic
education? Where where is too much AI?
>> There's in uh Pope Leo's most recent
letter that he released about a week ago
at this point, he warns of different uh
extremes. One of them is the
technophobia, which is the let's run
back to the caves uh mentality.
uh which you know sometimes sounds
attractive but then when you fully think
about what that life looks like probably
not as attractive as maybe at an initial
glance it might sound. uh and the other
is a digital reductionism right that at
an extreme again commodifies learning uh
eliminates humans from that process and
I I think as a starting point um I look
at antiquet nova which directly says
that the use of artificial intelligence
in when I say directly I don't mean this
is a quote but this is a paraphrasing
from from Antiquette no that the use of
artificial intelligence in educational
settings needs to accompany a human
relationship between student and teacher
and I think that's the right way to
frame it. Um, absent that, I think we
start to potentially open ourselves up
to uh some real problems. I think our
our classrooms need to be places of
physical encounter. Um, as much as that
can be possible when we need external
technologies, whether that's AI, whether
that's a textbook, whether whatever that
is, great. But as long as that is
oriented towards um human flourishing
again in the physical uh context of the
classroom, facilitating those
relationships. No, that's like a highle
place to start, but I think that the
prudence that's required to actually
unpack where do we draw those lines
requires a number of different factors.
How old are students developmentally?
Where are they? What again college
setting is very different than the
elementary school setting, right? And
and so I think there's a number of
factors that we need to start weighing
up. But it's those high level things
about uh the relationship between
teacher and student uh the incarnational
nature of our classrooms that I think
really should be the the starting
points.
>> Yeah. I think rather than a line, you
know, you asked is where's the line that
you don't cross? I think it's a it's a
bigger question of what's the purpose of
of this interaction between the person
and and the machine. What's the desired
outcome? Um and so we've been thinking
about this um for the past year as we
designed this this new use of AI and
this new curriculum and kind of settled
on three pillars that help guide us to
answer the set of questions that that
are related to what you're saying. And
the first is that we could should
conceive of these interactions with a
human and a and an AI or some emerging
technology as a human machine team with
the human being as the principal
protagonist in in this interaction the
center the human person since we know we
as we talked about earlier we know what
a human being is made in the image and
likeness of God he should be at the
center of this interaction with machine
and so there's a proper ordering to this
interaction and an improper
ordering and the improper ordering leads
to bad stuff or can lead to bad stuff.
So yeah, it should be should be thought
of as using this tool for a person. Um
and then the second pillar is this
flourishing. It should this interaction
should open up a window for the human
being to flourish. There should be a new
opportunity for the human to grow in
virtue and um and that's if you design
it on purpose that way you know you can
you can up your chances that that's
likely to happen. Uh and you should do
you should uh you should avoid strictly
the opposite. should never design this
type of interaction to encourage vice,
right? To, you know, which is going to
be hurting somebody. Like if you
designed an artificial girlfriend, like
that human, that boy, that young man is
not going to flourish. He's not going to
grow in virtue. He's not going to love.
So that's number two. Uh and then the
third is that it we mentioned it I think
earlier this morning. It should lead to
an authentic human interaction. You know
that the example you gave is it should
it should lead to you know let's we're
all in class together for 90 minutes
discussing face to face you know what we
think and asking questions. That's a
that's an authentic human interaction
right? So if it leads to that type of
interaction, like maybe you used AI to
do some research on on John to prepare
for this podcast.
>> I absolutely did.
>> But here we are. Here we are, you know,
sharing some jokes and and growing in
friendship. And that that's a good
that's a that's a good human
interaction. I think to to follow up on
two of the the things you said, one of
my favorite use cases that I've I've
experienced from or at least heard from
from teachers is the idea that they will
encourage their students to use whatever
the approved version of of you know,
Gemini or whatever whatever the tool is
at their school to prepare for in-class
debates.
>> Yeah. whether it's from research or even
just practicing delivering a a you know
a portion of the debate having it
critiqued by again whatever the tool is
to better facilitate an inerson
encounter because I think that's the
right orientation right I think that the
the second pillar that you outlined that
idea of human flourishing gets right
back to the job question yeah
>> because I think I mean I can speak
personally about this that
>> it's really hard for me at times to
separate my own personal identity from
my work
>> because it's so intrinsically just part
of who I am right and that's been my you
know, journey. But I don't think I'm
alone in that. And I think especially as
we race towards some form of job loss,
no matter how big or small that is,
there's a potential existential cliff
that people are going to face when they
realize like, oh, this thing that I did
that defined me in a sense is gone. What
is the purpose of my life? What and
that's where the question about how do
we define and explain human flourishing?
This is not a Catholic education issue.
This is a Catholic church pastoral
issue. Well, I mean that's that's what
partially what Ram Navarum was about.
And so I think um Ram Navarum 2.0 that
Pope Leo's probably going to write. Um
you know work is human dignity. Like
work leads to human dignity especially
for men just because of the differences
in in families. Um you know giving a man
a just wage to do honorable work gives
him dignity. And if you take that away
for some you know for some reason it it
hurts. like it it really hurts. So if
yeah now if now your entire
>> profession has been erased that's like
scary
>> and I think it's even more acute right
now because most of the research that
I've read is that the job loss currently
is impacting junior level employees
which is basically folks coming out of
college because those are the types of
tasks that can be automated right now.
So, as we think again in parishes and in
other ministries about how do we uh what
are the pastoral issues especially for
that demographic of 20 to 25 that's
going to be a real need but then
certainly that's going to scale um over
time as as AI improves and also in the
optimistic settings where they're like
oh yeah don't worry you know the the
your material needs your material goods
will be provided at you know at a
fraction of the cost and you'll have
more time to do the the things that we
do want to do the things of leisure
contemplation all that stuff which which
sounds great but I am very wary of
unearned pleasure, unearned comfort.
Like I as as a man, but also as as as
someone who's industrious and wants to
work, I grow so much when I'm when I'm
learning, when I'm being stretched, when
I'm being challenged. And I think that
like I am I think like something that I
I don't know I don't know if this is
directly something in education, but
that that that ability in education for
people to find their vocations then to
have a vision of how to get there.
>> Yeah. Um well I think defining not even
defining but exploring what true leisure
looks like is a great need in like our
families in our schools uh other
institutions because this is something
that people wrote about like 75 years
ago right or maybe not quite that long
ago but that we yearn for this freedom
but when we achieve freedom what are we
going to spend it on and I think again
there's a great need in in our
educational institutions to again orient
us in the right direction to be able to
experience leisure if and when that
becomes more readily available.
>> Yeah, I certainly I certainly need more
of that.
>> I think what what is it called?
Utripelia when you're not you don't uh
you don't know how to relax.
>> Like I don't know how to like go on
vacation.
My my uh my wife's grandmother often
speaks about how different vacations
were for their family after the
invention of uh the car phone because
prior to the car phone, a vacation was
true separation.
>> But after the car phone,
>> you were always at least sort of
accessible. And I think with every
digital technology since then, that's
just been ramped up, right?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Now there there is no off
switch in a weird way.
>> Yeah. Until you go camping in the
mountains, which is what we love to do,
too.
>> Yeah. Me, too. And so just to kind of
wind down here um as AI accelerates um
Dr. Dominguez and John what practical
steps in training and partnerships and
strategic investments can uh Catholic
institutions um integrate AI effectively
to lead in this transformation?
Well, one I'll give you just some
concrete examples and can pull back from
there. Um so we're we're a unique
university in the United States in that
we're the pontipical the national
pontipical university the only one and
um founded by the all the US bishops. So
in a sense like we serve we serve the
church of the United States uh and the
bishops and that's our that's the per
one of the main purposes of our
university and this is a leadership
class that's extremely important in the
church and um probably very few of them
are current in AI maybe one or two like
the guys who have their podcasts are
probably probably up to speed on a lot
of stuff but many of them aren't. So, um
this is this is the code I use for it as
a more polite term, but we've created a
boot camp AI boot camp for bishops.
>> Yeah. Which is going to go live here um
hopefully pretty soon before their
November meeting. But that and it's just
kind of basic stuff. It's a set of
15minute modules that Taylor Black has
helped us put together and um it's
asynchronous and delivered online and
it's firewalled off so it's not
currently not publicly accessible. just
just for those men right now. Um but
that's that's because they need to
understand like the language like the
words that's where we began and then you
know what are the set of tools what are
the kind of good things you can do with
this how can you use this for your
dascese for your business you know how
can you how can you help your priests so
a series of modules like that so that's
something um that we're well suited to
to do given our uh you know our
existence as the Catholic University of
America Um,
>> so there's that and then there's then
there's those just the education of our
students that I mentioned before. Um,
and then producing shows like this,
right? We we have to think through this
stuff.
>> It's been really heartening to see
different individuals and institutions
uh jumping into the fray. Um, there have
been frameworks released there. I I mean
even this morning in our uh education
breakout we had uh a gentleman talking
about a set of resources that he's
putting online and and making available
for parishes to think through you know
again these core questions of what are
the terms what is AI how do we approach
it um so the growing bank of resources I
has been good I think the only challenge
we might run into there is we we might
overwhelm uh the faithful who who are
looking for okay where do I go to get a
good information there's 300 frameworks
there's 300 uh sets of video modules. So
I I think that the more that we can be
precise about okay this is a particular
need that my institution or me
individually that I can fill the better.
U but I I think that I love the idea of
addressing the language that we use
because there's so many interesting
semantic questions around artificial
intelligence even just that term itself
is fascinating. So to to start by
unpacking what is that term and then
some of the related definitions and
ideas and then I think the fundamental
orientations about um instead of just
saying let's use AI, it's what are the
problems you're trying to solve. Okay,
great. Let's start with those and then
start attacking them by plugging in
solutions. So those are the kinds of uh
resources that I think are most helpful
for folks.
>> Yeah,
>> that is fantastic. Um thank you so much
Dr. Erin Dominguez and John Bear for
joining me today on this podcast. I want
to let you go back to the builder's AI
forum to continue to work on these
important problems. Thank you so much.
>> Thank you for having us.
>> Yeah. Thank you. Thank you, Dr. Yeah.
Thank you.